CANDY: I grew up
with the American dream.
ERIKA: But all Asian immigrants
were denied the right of
naturalized citizenship and with
the Exclusion Act,
the Chinese became the first
undocumented immigrants.
CANDY: The American Dream is
a lovely dream to have and so
people continue to aspire;
enduring whatever it is that
they've got to do as immigrants.
HELEN: Japanese Americans fought
on the side the United States,
while the rest of their
family was incarcerated.
ERIKA: Legal challenges were so
important because they did not
have political power.
And as much as tragedy is
a part of our heritage here,
so is possibility.
MAN: Asian voices
are coming out.
ALEX: You've got these
young people fighting to
make change happen.
ALISA: They had to
assert their rights.
NOBUKO: It was like a giant
genie coming out of the bottle.
You couldn't put us back in.
THAHN: These were stories about
what it meant to be human.
What it meant to be resilient.
VIET: To transform the system
into something more just
for everyone, that's the hope
from which the Asian American
movement was born.
HARI: The country's changing
and people are freaking
out about it.
I keep hearing about the
year 2042 on the news.
For those of you
who don't know,
2042 according to census
figures is the year when
white people will be the
minority in this country.
They'll be 49% and
white people are
freaking out about it.
Don't freak out white people!
You were the minority when
you came to this country.
Things seem to have
worked out for you.
I first wanted to do
standup comedy when I saw
Margaret Cho do
standup on television.
She was a Korean American woman,
but as an Indian kid that was
as close as we were going to
get at that point.
MARGARET: I was in
Mobile, Alabama.
I was walking down the
street and this man
actually calls me a chink.
I mean actually
called me a chink.
I was so mad.
I just looked at
him and said chink.
I'm sorry.
Chinks are Chinese.
I'm Korean.
I'm a gook. All right.
Get like a redneck to
English dictionary.
HARI: That fearlessness.
She stood out and it made me
believe there was a chance
that I could perform in front
of people and be accepted.
The future that people in this
country seem to be afraid of.
Where there's many
different cultures,
where whites are the minority.
Yeah. I grew up
in the future.
That's Queens.
I was always surrounded by
diversity like if anything,
I was sheltered in diversity,
I just assumed the whole
country was like
Queens, New York.
NARRATOR: When Hari's parents
came to the United States,
they were part of a historic
wave of new immigrants who
would change America.
Today Asians in America are
making their presence felt,
as the country's fastest
growing racial group.
In a time where we find
ourselves increasingly
polarized, Asian Americans are
playing an essential role in
the future of America.
In the late 1970s refugees
are escaping war-torn
Southeast Asia, and coming
to the United States.
They settle in the big cities,
but they also move to small
towns across the country.
MEE: Growing up, I always
identify as being Hmong,
not even Hmong-American.
My family came to the
United States in 1978.
We were refugees in the
aftermath of the Vietnam War.
I grew up in the Midwest.
And I remember walking my
brothers and sisters to school
and we would have cars go by.
People would throw their
ashtrays out the window at us,
you know, give us the finger.
They would say, you know,
"Chink, gook, go back
to your own country."
I didn't grow up
with a consciousness that
actually there were
other Asian Americans
experiencing similar things.
It felt very isolating.
Uh, and it felt like we
just had to suck it up.
NARRATOR: Mee Moua's
perspective would be
drastically transformed by
an event that will rock
the Asian American community.
It happens in Detroit on
a summer night in 1982.
REPORTER: Was
Vincent Chin beaten to death
with a baseball bat
because he was Oriental?
The brutal slaying has
outraged the Chinese community
in Detroit, and
across the nation.
HELEN: I had gone to Detroit
in the mid-seventies to be
involved in community
organizing and to learn about
the Heartland of America.
I actually arrived in Detroit
when the auto industry was
still booming and I got hired
in as a large press operator
in a Chrysler corporation
stamping plant.
These were well paid
jobs with full benefits.
The city had millions of
people whose livelihoods for
generations have been based
on a manufacturing economy.
Then the bottom fell out.
NARRATOR: In 1979 Detroit's
automakers are devastated by
an international oil crisis.
Gas prices skyrocket.
Consumers start buying fuel
efficient foreign cars and
sales of American-made
cars plummet.
By 1982 one in five Detroit
residents are unemployed.
HELEN: People lost their futures
and their children's futures.
Pretty soon the finger of
blame ended up on Japan.
All of this hatred.
You could feel it.
It was palpable.
REPORTER: Detroiters
were invited for 50 cents a
smash to take out their
anger on Japanese cars.
HELEN: It was in that climate
of intense hatred that a
27 year old Chinese American
was getting ready for his
all American bachelor party.
NARRATOR: Vincent Chin is
the only child of a Chinese
immigrant couple, who adopted
him because they couldn't have
children of their own.
As a teenager he was a
football player with a wide
circle of friends.
By the summer of 1982, he's
all set for a June wedding
to his long-time
girlfriend, Vicky.
HELEN: A week
before his wedding,
he was out with his buddies
at a bar in Detroit.
REPORTER: Inside the bar,
43 year old Ronald Ebens,
a foreman at a
Chrysler auto plant,
and his 23 year old stepson
Michael Nitz taunted Chin,
mistaking him for Japanese
and accusing him for the
economic downfall of
the US auto industry.
NARRATOR: The fight ends up
outside where the assailants
hunt down Chin
and his friends.
REPORTER:
According to witnesses,
Ebens took this bat out of
the trunk of his car and
repeatedly used it to hammer
and crush Chin's skull.
As his friends held him,
his last words were,
"It isn't fair.
It isn't fair."
NARRATOR: Vincent's killers
plead guilty to manslaughter
and face 15 years in prison.
But Judge Charles Kaufman
sentences them to
three years' probation
and a $3,000 fine.
He says, "These aren't the
kind of men you send to prison""
VIET: I think theVincent Chin murder was
shocking to a lotof Asian Americans.
Not because itrepresented something new,
but that it actually
represented something old.
It reminded Asian-Americans
that progress
hadn't really been made.
HELEN: In 1882 you could
kill a quote China man and
get off paying $1.
In 1982 you can kill an
Asian American and get off
paying $3,000.
This was not justice, but
there wasn't an organization
that existed to stand up
and say, this is wrong.
What began out of that was
meetings that started with
four people, 10 people,
20 people, 100 people,
and people were talking
about what can we do?
What can we do?
I raised my hand and I said,
the world wants to know how
the Asian American
community feels about this.
CROWD: We want justice.
We want justice.
REPORTER: In death.
Vincent Chin inspired
protest marches, rallies,
dinners, banquets.
GROUP: Justice for Vincent Chin!
HELEN: The killing of
Vincent Chin is probably the
most tragic example of the kind
of violence that's being
committed against Asians.
JEFF: For Asian Americans,
Vincent Chin's murder
symbolized an extreme
example of the kind of
discrimination that they'd face.
It becomes a rallying
point for Asian Americans
to be able to say,
"That's me too."
MEE: I was a freshman in
college when I heard about
Vincent Chin and the impact on
the Asian American community.
And it was the first time that
I felt like my experience as a
Hmong refugee, as a Southeast
Asian was connected to the
experience of other
Asian Americans.
I am finally a piece of the
puzzle that completes the
picture and it
was so liberating.
HELEN: Civil rights
organizations of every kind
came forward as
well as individuals.
JESSE: We have been
drawn together by death,
an unplanned family reunion,
our hearts are made heavy
by a mother who sits here
with us whose
son was brutally killed just
because he was, what can
we do in the aftermath?
Those who live, we
must redefine America,
So that everybody
knows everybody fits
in the rainbow somewhere.
HELEN: Mrs. Chin was the
inspirational and spiritual
leader of this movement.
Many of the ways that she's
been seen is to remember her
as a grieving mother, but to
know her, she was a strong,
outspoken woman.
LILY: You know how
they killed my son?
Killed my son.
Like they kill an animal.
DONAHUE: Like they kill
an animal. Yes ma'am.
LILY: This made me very angry.
DONAHUE: Yes ma'am.
HELEN: Lilly Chin's husband
had just died six months
before Vincent was
attacked and killed.
Her son had already been
shopping and looking for a
house that would have a room
for his mother to live in and
there was nothing more
that Mrs. Chin wanted
than to have grandchildren.
Even through her pain.
She was standing up,
speaking up, organizing.
LILY: I don't want any other
mother to suffer like me.
HELEN: We began to look at the
different civil rights laws.
There were constitutional
law professors who
came out and said,
"Civil rights laws
are only meant to protect
African Americans."
We had to talk to them and
say, no, that's not true.
As an Asian American, he was
being isolated and targeted
and scapegoated because of his
race in this climate of hate.
So of course, civil
rights laws should apply.
NARRATOR: Under
mounting pressure,
the Justice Department
agrees to bring charges.
This is the first hate-crime
prosecution involving
an Asian American.
Ronald Ebens is found guilty
of violating Vincent's
civil rights and is sentenced
to 25 years in prison.
But his conviction is
overturned on appeal.
Neither he nor his
stepson will ever serve
a day in prison for
Vincent's murder.
LILY: I wanted justice for
my son, this is not fair...
MEE: All the things that went
wrong didn't give justice to
Vincent's mom, but what
it did do was it invited
Asian Americans to search
our voices and demand that
we are seeing beyond being
the perpetual foreigner,
but that we actually belong.
This is our country.
HELEN: Vincent Chin's
case has a legacy that
affects all Americans.
Even to this day.
MEE: A hate crime now is
not just an act committed
on somebody because
of who they are, but
because of who the perpetrator
perceived them to be.
That's one of the
concrete legacies
of the Vincent Chin case.
NARRATOR: Mee Moa's activism
led her to a career as the
first Hmong
politician in the U.S.
Though she came to this
country as a refugee,
she was elected to the
Minnesota senate in 2002,
where she will
serve for 8 years.
The early 1980s is
a tipping point:
the Asian American population
flips from majority US-born
to largely foreign-born.
New neighborhoods pop up
all over the United States.
One of the biggest is in
the heart of Los Angeles,
an enclave that comes to
be known as Koreatown.
ANGELA: Koreatown was a
physical space where you could
migrate here and never have
to encounter the mainstream.
We had our grocery stores,
our restaurants,
watch repair stores,
wig shops, you name it.
You could transact daily life
without breaking into English.
ALEX: When I think
about Koreatown,
I really think about the
Sundays with my family.
It would be like a whole day,
we'd like go
there in the morning,
go to church service.
And then after that we'd go
and have like a family meal
together and my parents
would go to the video store.
For our family and
many families a store
was like a second home.
We had birthday parties
there and I know a lot of
Korean American store owners
had a little cot in the back
or someplace where
people ate meals.
(singing in Korean)
NARRATOR: Korean immigrants
like Alex's parents look for
opportunities where the cost
of business is affordable.
For many, this means looking
beyond the borders of
Koreatown in places
like South Los Angeles.
These neighborhoods are
predominantly black and
Latinx, with their own
identities and histories.
BRENDA: Many people of color
and African Americans in
particular were
disappointed, frustrated, um,
agitated about, um,
social conditions,
about the lack of jobs,
about policing in Los Angeles.
And so you have an African
American community that in
some ways is like an immigrant
community because we've never
been completely integrated
within the society.
NARRATOR: In March of 1991, the
world watches as Los Angeles
police officers beat a 26
year old African American
man named Rodney King.
ANGELA: Back then in the 90s,
I was just a lawyer when a
number of us who practiced
in that area saw that video.
Our reaction was, well, it's
about time the rest of the
world see what happens on
the streets of South LA.
MAN: We are not
going to take this racist
police brutality
in our streets.
HELEN: Unfortunately in our
Asian American community,
many of the newer immigrants
who come have no idea of the
civil rights
history in America.
ANGELA: The civil rights laws
that came into effect in the
60s were the product
of huge fights,
mostly led by
African Americans.
Sacrifices that were made
by African Americans.
None of this was appreciated
by the majority of new
immigrants who came
after the fact.
ALEX: You know, my parents
didn't have any understanding
that there was the civil
rights movement or the
history of racial
equality in this country.
They didn't know
anything about that.
ANGELA: In South L.A.
you had a region that was
historically an established
African American community
being transformed into
a Latinx community.
There's competition for jobs.
There's competition
for housing.
BRENDA: Close to 70% of
businesses were owned by
Korean Americans.
There was a notion that
the shop owners had been
disrespectful, had
been dismissive.
MAN: Yeah, prices are high.
Their attitude is wrong and
they just don't seem to have
any respect for the
black community.
ANGELA: In the
Korean community,
there's an anxiety because
there was a lot of news about
assaults, robberies, shootings
that were being reported in,
in language news, but if you
read the LA times Metro section,
all you read about when
it came to Koreans was
how rude they were,
how racist they were.
JEFF: What we see is a lot
of media trying to play up
Asian and black tensions.
ALEX: I'm sure that's a much
easier narrative to build and
write than something about the
hundreds of years of racial
inequality and social
inequality in America.
BRENDA: Latasha Harlins was a
15 year old African American
girl who lived in
South Central Los Angeles.
She went into a grocery
slash liquor store in her
neighborhood on March 16th,
1991 to purchase a bottle of
orange juice for $1.79.
The proprietress Mrs. Soon Ja Du
accuses her of stealing,
pulls her across the counter.
Latasha responds by punching
her, a fight ensues.
Latasha bends down to pick up
the orange juice and Mrs. Du
has stood up with
a gun in her hand.
Latasha turns to walk
out of the store and
she shot in the
back of the head.
JEFF: This particular incident
comes to represent all these
grievances that have
been building up.
REPORTER: A jury convicted
Du of voluntary manslaughter.
A pre-sentence report
recommended the maximum
16 years, but judge Joyce
Karlin imposed probation,
a $500 fine, no jail time.
JEFF: This is literally
10 years after the
killing of Vincent Chin.
Wasn't the equivalent to
Vincent Chin, Latasha Harlins?
But in this case, certain
Asian-Americans organized
to support Soon Ja Du.
HELEN: And instead of being
seen as a part of the
multiracial coalition,
suddenly Korean Americans
were seen as just like
those racist LA cops
who beat up Rodney King.
MAN: Go home
CROWD: Go home!
HELEN: People on the ground
within the Korean American and
African American communities
were trying to signal this
could be a problem.
Then all hell broke loose.
REPORTER: The
verdict stunned almost
everyone except the four
officers acquitted of
beating Rodney King.
Sheriff's deputies escorted
them from the courthouse to
face a hostile crowd.
ANGELA: We had five days
of looting, burning, arson,
chaos really in
the city of L.A.
CROWD: No justice, no peace.
No justice, no peace.
ANGELA: The fire department,
they felt unsafe rolling out.
So the city burned.
I mean I counted at one point
19 fires going simultaneously.
ALEX: I remember the whole
scene playing out on TV.
Much as the first Gulf War
played out on TV that it was
kind of, I don't know,
infotainment in a way.
REPORTER: Though the
riots were sparked by the
verdicts in the
Rodney King case.
They were fueled by
growing hostilities
between blacks and Koreans.
ALEX: I remember
my father said,
he knew that this wasn't good.
That this media narrative that
Koreans and black people
were in this conflict.
BRENDA: As people left
South central and went up to
Koreatown, Latasha's name
was heard on the streets.
You know, "This is for Latasha.
This is for Latasha."
ANGELA: The police were
not coming to protect
any of these stores.
Most of them owned by
immigrant families from Korea.
The Korean community itself
went over the airwaves and
they were calling for
people to show up wherever
they could with arms.
A lot of the men
in the community,
first generation immigrants
had served in the military
'cause it's
mandatory in Korea.
So they had firearms, they
knew how to use firearms
and they started defending
their own stores.
ALEX: The strongest
memory I have, the one
that goes deepest is I had a
conversation with my father,
we sat on the couch
in our living room.
He came and sat
down next to me.
He said that the violence
and looting in Koreatown was
getting really bad and that
he had to go and defend the
store, that he had obtained
a gun and that he was
going to go down there.
And um...
Even now it's a very
painful memory that, um,
basically he may
not come back.
NARRATOR: Alex's parents'
store is destroyed along with
more than 2,000 other
Korean owned businesses.
WOMAN: This is America.
We have to stand our pride.
Human dignity.
Where is your human dignity?
We are human beings,
we have to have dignity.
We don't do things like this.
JEFF: I mean it was, it was
one of those moments that
actually really changed my
life because it was like
war had broken out and
I knew people that
I deeply loved on both sides.
And for me, you know, I
had come up really deeply
believing in this third world
strike ideal and this idea of,
of a rainbow coalition,
it was like,
not just people whose
lives were at stake,
but also our revolutionary
dreams are kind of
going up in smoke.
NARRATOR: As a result of
the unrest in Los Angeles,
63 people lose their lives,
with damages estimated
at $1 billion.
ALEX: Because the rioting had
destroyed their businesses,
my family's financial
situation changed drastically,
had to move from
where we were living.
They were under tremendous
stress to figure out what
they're going to do to,
like feed me and my brother.
That trauma stayed with them,
like marked them as people.
I made a documentary about
my family's experience
with the riots.
ALEX: After the riots,
my parents and I barely
discussed it, so the film was
a way for me and my parents
to like engage about it.
ALEX: I think about
when I should tell
my daughter about riots.
Like when is she old enough
for me to explain the riots
are part of her family's
journey here in this country.
I wouldn't be able to speak
of our experiences in this
country, our immigrant story,
without talking about that.
I recognize now the reason
that Koreatown burned down.
That was a neighborhood that
was brought up, established,
populated by people who are
themselves marginalized.
If those businesses were in the
well-heeled parts of this town,
do you think that the
mayor would let that burn down?
Never.
They would go down themselves
to protect those places.
There's no way that they
would let that happen.
So, you know, we were victims
as well, of this system.
(inaudible chanting)
CROWD: We want justice.
We want justice.
ANGELA: There was a
consciousness that woke
out of the fire and the chaos
and the crisis that hit LA.
Korean America
was born in 1992.
NARRATOR: On May 2nd as
the violence subsides,
30,000 people gather in
Koreatown for a peace rally.
ANGELA: It was a huge March that
took us down Olympic Boulevard.
That kind of diversity that
you would expect to see in LA.
There were African Americans,
there were Latinos,
there were Koreans,
there were whites.
Everyone was present.
We wanted to send a message
that we also want justice and
we also want peace.
BRENDA: We had emerging now
these new leaders within the
Korean American community
and this leadership has been
working with African American
leadership to move forward.
MAN: We have a dream as
late Martin Luther King
had a dream.
That we together will be
able to establish a nation of
justice and peace and
we are here to stay.
VIET: My parents
were shopkeepers.
And I think it would take a
little bit of time for me to
think through what all
these things meant.
Like every population,
Asian Americans have
choices to make.
They can dwell on their own
victimization which is a
choice that is there for
every so-called minority
and for the majority.
They can choose to
side with power or
to be complicit with power.
And to be perpetrators or to
at least enjoy the profits of
being aligned
with perpetrators.
Or they could refuse these kinds
of choices and instead seek to
transform the system
into something more just,
more equitable for everyone.
That's the hope of activism,
that's the hope of solidarity.
That's the hope of alliance,
that's the hope and the
conviction from which
something like the Asian
American movement was born.
MOM: Margaret, do you know
why I encourage your brother
to become a cardiologist?
MARGARET: No.
MOM: Because I always
knew that one day
you give me a heart attack,
what are you wearing!
RANDALL: In 1994 I remember
"All-American Girl" coming out
and it being a big
deal because it was uh,
an Asian family on TV.
MARGARET: I'm American,
Eric is American,
even Stuart is American.
Tell her.
RANDALL: And I remember there
being criticisms of the show
and even from within
like, the community,
but I remember watching it and
just thinking it was like so
great to see this
and normalizing,
HARI: Well there was a whole
group of films in like the
late 90s all about like
a middle class Indian life.
MAN: Leaving the house
is leaving the house
no matter where you go.
And just be a good boy
and let her do a poojah.
HARI: And they were terrible.
But that's, you know, we
had to create art for,
for us to represent our stories
'cause they weren't being told.
WOMAN: Okay, looks nice,
now smile naturally mom.
MOM: I always do...
WOMAN 2: You look younger all
the time, how is that?
MOM 2: I give you my good skin,
you will look like me when...
VIET: I went to a local
bookstore and came across
Amy Tan's "The Joy Luck Club",
which had just come out.
I had never seen a book before
written by an Asian-American
about Asian-Americans.
And even if it wasn't
about Vietnamese people,
it was close enough.
I was like, wow, this
is an amazing book.
And I can't believe the
story is being told and
in such a powerful way.
JERRY: The kinds of stories I
heard from my grandmother who
escaped to mainland China in
1949 by herself with five kids.
For my kids' generation,
it's like fairy tale.
It's hard to believe that
war was 60 years ago.
You know, in some ways she
hated the country she came
from because the
Communists tortured her.
She never looked back.
But her mission in life
was to make sure her kids
and then her grandkids
had it better.
NARRATOR: Jerry Yang
was born in Taiwan,
and was 2 years old
when his father died.
His widowed mother decided to
emigrate the family to America.
When he arrived he only knew
one word of English, shoe.
JERRY: My mom was a single
mother and I was the first born,
so I was expected to
go to college, get a job,
make money so my mom doesn't
have to pay for us anymore.
NARRATOR: Jerry is accepted
to Stanford University.
There, he forms a partnership
with fellow student David Filo.
The two of them create a
business that changes
the way that Americans
engage with the world.
MAN: Do you, uh, Yahoo?
JERRY: When the worldwide web
started in 1989 we had this
explosion of content that
you'd never had before.
David and I said, Hey, maybe
we can try to keep track of
all these websites
that are coming online.
We had no idea that it
would be a business.
For the longest
time it was called
Jerry's Guide to
the Worldwide Web.
By the end of the 1994
we were one of the largest
websites in the world.
You're literally laying
down the train tracks
as the train is running.
And you just got to
stay ahead of it.
OANH: I was a young
reporter in Silicon Valley,
started at the
Mercury News in 1998.
It was a really exciting
time because, you know,
the tech boom was in full mode.
You really felt this was at
the center of where things
were going to happen that was
going to change the world.
ANNALEE: In the early 90s
supplies of white and
native born talent really dried
up and you started to see the
influx in large numbers of
highly skilled Asian immigrants.
Close to 40% of the new startups
were from Asian entrepreneurs.
OANH: You know,
Asian-Americans have been a
very important part of the
rise of big industries.
You know in the 1860s you
had the Chinese who were
so integral to building the
transcontinental railroad.
Going into the 21st century
there were Asian Americans
who were becoming founders
with fantastic visions.
If you were lucky enough to
have gone to American schools
and get a US education,
Silicon Valley and that
boom was fantastic for them.
There were a lot of people
who had to do the hard work
of actually manufacturing
the guts of what goes into
computers at the time.
And those people,
unfortunately though they were
immigrants from China,
immigrants from Vietnam,
most of them didn't have the
college education that these
other engineers did.
They basically would be
putting transistors on circuit
boards and getting
paid by the piece.
For every printed circuit
board that you finished.
And that's why it's
called piece work.
Some of the biggest names
in Silicon Valley were using
Asian immigrant workers
to do piece work at home.
We ended up doing a nine
month investigation into
piece work in Silicon Valley.
We were looking at violations
that included child labor,
minimum wage violations.
So you do have kind of this
barbell division, right,
where you have Asian Americans
at the very top who are doing
really well, who are
the model minorities.
And at the very bottom
you also have a different
flavoring of Asian Americans
who are really struggling.
A lot of them were refugees
like myself and my family.
You know, there
weren't too many people in the
"San Jose Mercury"
newsroom who can go into the
Vietnamese American community to
ask them about piece work.
You know, in the aftermath,
I just realized that as
a journalist of color,
I need to be able to tell
the stories of my community.
NARRATOR: Jerry Yang draws
from his own bicultural
experience as an immigrant
to become a maverick of the
internet revolution.
JERRY: During the starting
of the internet craze, and
starting Yahoo! I still
identified as Asian American.
There was no question.
But especially when I went
back to Asia to do business,
my identity really helped.
ANNALEE: Immigrants were
part of opening up India.
Apple wouldn't be in
China without the help
of Asian immigrants.
You wouldn't have
manufacturing in Taiwan.
Many pieces of the global
economy are fueled by the
contributions of the Asian
immigrants in Silicon Valley.
JERRY: If you look
at our children,
they live in a more global
world today than we did
30 years ago, but in
many ways more divided.
And for me, making sure
they know who they are,
the history of the places
that they come from,
first and foremost, America.
You want to prepare them
to be the most impactful
citizens of their community
that they can be.
In many ways, that's
what my mom did for us
by moving to the US.
When people's backs are
against the wall and there's
nowhere else to go,
you go forward.
TEREZA: I started playing piano
when I was seven years old.
We couldn't afford lessons,
but my dad made me practice
three hours a day every day.
My parents are
from South Korea.
They fled the aftermath of the
Korean War to South America.
I was born in Brazil and
when I was two years old,
we came to the United States.
Soon after my little
brother was born.
When I was seven years old,
my dad sat the whole family
around in the living
room and he said,
"I have a very serious secret
to tell you and that is that,
we are undocumented."
My dad said that if anyone
found out we were undocumented,
my parents would be sent
to the South Korea and
I would be sent to Brazil.
My brother, who was
born in Chicago,
sent to some foster care
because he's a US born citizen.
That made us become muted.
The fear of
separation is real.
We grew up having
nightmares of the police
storming up our stairs and
breaking our doors down
and taking our family away.
NARRATOR: The piano
is Tereza's sanctuary.
She gets a scholarship at
a music school in Chicago.
The artistic director
Ann Monaco takes Tereza
under her wing.
TEREZA: She proceeded to print
out 10 college applications
for me and she said, fill them
out and bring them back to me
as soon as you can.
She saw that my social
security number was blank.
She saw that my birthplace was
Brazil and she looked at me
and said, you were
born in Brazil?
I burst into tears and
begged her to not turn
me into the police.
She said, "Tereza,
do you trust me?"
NARRATOR: Ann Monaco makes
a plea on Tereza's behalf
to their Senator, Dick Durbin.
DICK: Tereza Lee, under
the eyes of the law in the
United States was undocumented.
She was in the
United States illegally.
The law said the only thing
Tereza could do was leave the
United States for 10 years
and apply to come back.
Uh, I thought that was
a terrible outcome.
NARRATOR: Senator Durbin
drafts an immigration bill
specifically for Tereza
that puts her on a path to
citizenship and college,
but in the process,
he hears from more students
facing the same dilemma.
DICK: We realized
she was not alone.
There were thousands
just like her.
TEREZA: He needed to redraft
the whole thing into a larger
bill and that became
known as the "DREAM Act."
NARRATOR: The "DREAM Act" would
open a path to citizenship
for undocumented children
who are brought to the
country as minors.
To qualify, they must
either join the military
or attend college.
They become known as dreamers.
DICK: The first
dreamer was Tereza Lee.
My mother was an
immigrant to this country.
She didn't become a citizen
until she was in her
mid-20s, a mother
with two children.
If you're here through
no fault of your own,
you ought to have a chance
to prove yourself and
be part of America's future.
NARRATOR: The DREAM Act
is cosponsored by
Republican Senator Orrin Hatch.
The bill attracts
overwhelming support on
both sides of the aisle.
TEREZA: 2001 we
had a hearing set,
62 votes were lined up
and president Bush was
ready to sign it into law.
I was set to perform a little
concert for the senators.
I was ready to fly to DC
and the subways were closed.
There were no cabs available.
Everyone was talking
about this attack.
BRYANT: It's 8:52
here in New York.
I'm Bryant Gumbel.
We understand that there has
been a plane crash on the
southern tip of Manhattan.
You're looking at the
World Trade Center.
HARI: 9/11 happened
when I was in college,
so I was so far from home.
My brother went to
Stuyvesant High School,
which is not that far from
where the Twin Towers were,
so that day was horrible
for everybody 'cause
my city was attacked.
I don't know where
my brother is.
I'm very far away.
I feel very alone.
REPORTER: The terrorist attacks
have united much of America,
but some Arab
Americans are feeling left out.
Fearful they could become the
next target of misguided anger.
Since Tuesday's attacks, the
FBI reports 40 hate crimes,
suspected retaliation.
HARI: You had a lot of people
being beaten up because they
were brown skin, because
they were Muslim,
because they were Sikh.
REPORTER: In Mesa, Arizona,
a man from India was killed at
his convenience store because
he looked Middle Eastern.
HARI: One of the weird parts
about being a Brown person in
that post 9/11 era is
you get victimized twice.
Like on one hand you're
afraid of terrorism as much as
anybody else is at that point,
like that's all you're hearing
from the media.
And then your
country hates you.
They don't, they
don't say it openly,
but when people are
yelling things to you,
telling you to go back to
countries you're not even from
cause you're from America.
WOMAN: Go home.
You don't like America.
Leave this country.
We're proud to be Americans.
HARI: You start
to get the hint.
NORM: On Thursday, September
13 there was a cabinet meeting
with the House and Senate,
Democratic and
Republican leadership.
Congressmen from Detroit,
Michigan said, Mr. President,
we have a large population of
Middle Easterners and Muslims
and they're very concerned
about all the rhetoric.
President said, you're
absolutely correct.
We don't want to
have happen today
what happened to Norm in 1942.
MAN: Before arrival
at their new quarters,
the evacuees
voluntarily registered.
What this means for
the Japs, nobody knows.
What it means to us,
everybody knows.
HARI: And it didn't happen
again in the same way.
REPORTER: The
Bush administration has been
conducting a top secret
surveillance program
without warrants in
Muslim communities.
JEFF: What happens after 9/11
is immigration policy moves
from trying to create
pathways to citizenship,
to being wholly about closing
the door and deporting people.
TEREZA: Any immigrant
friendly legislation
was out of the question.
The DREAM Act was canceled
and that meant that the
undocumented
immigrants were at risk.
HARI: It wasn't so public,
let's round them up,
put them into camps.
But it was like,
quietly and quickly,
deport people,
arrest people.
Like the Ansar Mahmoud case.
ANSAR: My name
is Ansar Mahmoud.
I'm here for the something
happening after 9/11.
That's the reason I'm here.
NARRATOR: Born in Pakistan,
Ansar Mahmoud moved to
New York's Hudson Valley in
2000 after his dream came true:
he won a green card from
the immigration lottery.
ANSAR: I liked the quiet life,
you know, tried to relax.
Not too many people over
there, not too much noise.
All old houses.
I can see lots of mountains.
There's a nice river.
NARRATOR: One evening
in October 2001,
Ansar was taking photos of
the Hudson Valley landscape
to send home to his family.
He ducks behind a fence
to get a better view,
not realizing he has
stumbled onto the grounds
of a water treatment facility.
REPORTER: DPW crews
saw him and they did report
to the police.
Hudson PD then called the
FBI who contacted INS
and the state police.
HARI: And even
after they cleared him,
even after they said,
"Oh yea, this is just some
harmless guy taking a picture,"
they wanted to get rid of him.
REPORTER: In
searching his apartment,
federal authorities found he
had co-signed a lease for a
Pakistani couple who
had overstayed their visa.
HARI: It was fear.
Fear drove all of it.
REPORTER: One bigsource of comfort for Mahmood
is a group of people in
Hudson deeply concerned
about his case.
They are searching for
a way to keep him here.
CROWD: Free Ansar, free Ansar!
ANSAR: These people, they make
my spirit high and high hope.
I still believe this
country is good.
It's valuable.
You can live here,
you can work.
MAN: Even after
all that's happened?
ANSAR: Even after
all that's happened.
DICK: I rise today to speak
about an issue which is
timely and controversial.
It's the issue of immigration.
NARRATOR: After September 11th,
the DREAM Act is reintroduced a
number of times in the Senate,
but never achieves enough
votes to become law.
TEREZA: In 2012,
Dreamers started organizing.
(inaudible chanting)
CROWD: Now!
TEREZA: For the first time we
started seeing an immigration
movement, not just
undocumented immigrants,
but other Americans
coming out to support.
HELEN: On the one hand,
communities are now under
intense investigation.
On the other hand, it's also
brought communities together.
HARI: 9/11 happens.
I go from someone who's
sheltered in diversity and
fairly apolitical to
a politicized being.
I was an immigrant
rights organizer.
I worked with victims
of hate crimes,
people being detained
and deported,
and I wanted my standup,
my art form to reflect
what I believed.
I hate how immigrants are
talked about in this country.
I was watching CNN,
which was my mistake,
and they were interviewing
this woman in Arizona who is
against immigration, right?
And she said, look, we're just
trying to bring this country
back to the way it used to be.
The way it used to be!
Lady, you're in Arizona.
It used to be Mexico.
Growing up I always felt like
I had access to the world.
People from all
over the world.
Different races, religions,
people with status,
without status.
Like I felt, looking
back on it now,
I feel like I was
trained for the future.
NARRATOR: They were
seen as outsiders...
Dreamers who could
never become American.
But they were always American.
By arriving on these shores,
by seeking a better destiny,
by giving their all,
by building up the
nation rail by rail.
By claiming their space.
By striving for justice.
By struggling for the
rights of all people,
not just their own.
They have always been American.
HELEN: History has a
way of moving in cycles,
and if we can learn from
history even a little bit,
we can avoid repeating it.
But even better than that, we
can find the things that have
moved civilization forward and
have led to greater progress.
And if we learned from that,
we can really move ahead.
JEFF: The idea of being Asian
American originated in part as
a will to power.
As a way to be able to
say we've been stepped on,
we've been excluded,
we've been erased.
And you need to
recognize us now.
Because we're here and
we're not going away.
VIET: The very idea of the
Asian American contains
within itself an endless
range of possibilities...
Is a part of who we are!
CONNIE: We honor the courage,
fortitude and sacrifice of
Chinese railroad workers and
their legacy in America which
belongs to all of us!
ERICA: The Asian American
story is such a quintessential
American story because we,
as Asian Americans,
have represented
the polar extremes of
the American experience.
The most downtrodden and
discriminated against,
to rising to positions
of power and privilege.
To being singled
out for exclusion,
to being explicitly welcomed,
and included, and held up,
of the very best of America.
That is the story of America,
and that is the story
of Asian America.
NARRATOR: To order
Asian Americans on DVD,
visit ShopPBS.org
or call 1-800-PLAY-PBS
This program is also available
on Amazon Prime Video.